Finding Aid for the Joseph Chouinard Collection of Images, circa 1928-2006
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Joseph Chouinard Collection of Images, circa 1928-2006
Mus. Arc. 71.2
Chouinard, Joseph Jerod, 1926-2014
2 boxes (227 items)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The collection contains 227 images collected by Joseph Chouinard. The images provide documentation of his life from the age of about two years through age eighty. The collection contains images of his performances with opera companies in Maine, Binghamton, Buffalo, and elsewhere. The collection also contains images from the fourteen months Joseph Chouinard spent as a member of the United States Navy on Okinawa.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Joseph Chouinard, 2006.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Alternate Forms
Collection contents have been digitized and are available in University Libraries Digital Collections.
Biographical Note
Joseph Chouinard was born in Middletown, Connecticut. His birth certificate lists his middle name as Gerard and his date of birth as May 4th, 1926. However, later documentation shows his date of birth to be May 7th, 1926 and his middle name to be Jerod. It is unclear why this discrepancy exists, though it should be noted. He graduated from Middletown High School in 1944. Following graduation Joseph enlisted in the United States Navy. He served in the Navy from 1944-1946, during which time he was stationed in Okinawa, Japan. After he was discharged he attended the University of Connecticut, graduating with a BA in Music in 1950. He stayed at the university and in 1952, obtained his Master of Arts and Music Degree. Later, he obtained his MLS in Music Librarianship from State University of New York College at Geneseo in 1970. In addition to his degrees, Joseph studied with Nadia Boulanger at Fontainebleau in 1957 and 1958. He also attended the 1961 Session of the Summer School for Singers in Oxford, England.
Throughout his life, Joseph performed both nationally and internationally as a bass baritone. He performed both as a chorus member and as a soloist, including performances at the Tanglewood Festival, Calvary Church in New York City, the Tri-Cities Opera Company in Binghamton, the Aspen Music Festival, the Florida International Music Festival, Columbia University, Arundel Opera (Maine), Theatre Under the Stars in Atlanta, Georgia, and with the University Opera Studio at the State University of New York at Buffalo.
His music librarianship career included positions as Music and Art Librarian, California State College at San Bernardino (1971-1974), Music Cataloger, State University of New York at Buffalo (1974-1978), Music Librarian, State University of New York College at Fredonia (1978-1991), and Exchange Music Librarian at Royal Holloway College, Great Britain (1983-1984). After retiring, Joseph Chouinard remained active as a volunteer at the State University of New York at Buffalo Music Library and at the Buffalo Veterans Administration Hospital where he led patients in various arts activities such as readings of plays and poetry. He died in Buffalo on January 6th, 2014.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains 227 images collected by Joseph Chouinard. They document his life from the age of about two years through age eighty. The collection contains images of his performances with opera companies in Maine, Binghamton, Buffalo, and elsewhere. The collection also contains a set of twenty packaged images from Pikes Peak, Colorado and another set of forty-five images that document the fourteen months Joseph Chouinard spent as a United States sailor on Okinawa at the end of World War II. Mr. Donn Cuson generously provided information to identify many of the photographs in this set.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in six series based on format and size of material:
I. Larger format photographs
II. Medium format photographs
III. Smaller format photographs
IV. Drawings
V. 35 mm slides
VI. Oversize
Container List
- Large format photographs, circa 1930-May 2006, I.; Item 001-047
  Larger format photographs, including formal portraits.
  Arranged in roughly chronological order.
  - Portrait of an unidentified woman, possibly the mother or grandmother of Joseph Chouinard, undated, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Welker Studio (Middletown, Conn.) Location: Middletown (Conn.) (Box 1, Image 001)
  - Portrait of Joseph Chouinard and brother Thomas as young children, circa 1930, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Turner Studio (Middletown, Conn.) Location: Middletown (Conn.) (Box 1, Image 002)
  - Portrait of an unidentified woman, possibly Elizabeth Bradley, Joseph Chouinard's adoptive mother, circa 1930, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Unknown location (Box 1, Image 003)
  - Boys' choir of Holy Trinity Church in Middletown, Connecticut, circa 1936, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Middletown (Conn.) Venue: Church of the Holy Trinity (Middletown, Conn.) (Box 1, Image 004)
  - Portrait of Joseph Chouinard during his high school years, circa 1942, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Unknown location (Box 1, Image 005)
  - Portrait of Joseph Chouinard during his high school years, circa 1942, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Unknown location (Box 1, Image 006)
  - Portrait of Joseph Chouinard in his Navy uniform, circa 1944, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Loring Studio Location: Unknown location (Box 1, Image 007)
  - Portrait of Joseph Chouinard in his Navy uniform with his adoptive parents, George and Elizabeth Bradley, circa 1944, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Unknown location (Box 1, Image 008)
  - Drawing of Joseph Chouinard by Annis Martin, 1945, 1 drawing; Photographer: Martin, Annis Location: Unknown location (Box 1, Image 009)
  - Portrait of Joseph Chouinard during his college years, circa 1950, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Unknown location (Box 1, Image 010)
  - Joseph Chouinard on stage as the character Frank Butler and Celeste Maggiore as Annie Oakley in the Arundel Opera production of Annie get your gun, 1959 July 1, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Kennebunkport (Me.) Venue: Arundel Opera Theatre (Kennebunkport, Me.) (Box 1, Image 011)
  - Celeste Maggiore as Annie Oakley in Arundel Opera production of Annie get your gun, 1959 July 1, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Kennebunkport (Me.) Venue: Arundel Opera Theatre (Kennebunkport, Me.) (Box 1, Image 012)
  - Unidentified female character in Arundel Opera's production of Die Fledermaus, 1959 August, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Kennebunkport (Me.) Venue: Arundel Opera Theatre (Kennebunkport, Me.) (Box 1, Image 013)
  - Ballet scene from Arundel Opera's production of Die Fledermaus, 1959 August, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Kennebunkport (Me.) Venue: Arundel Opera Theatre (Kennebunkport, Me.) (Box 1, Image 014)
  - Joseph Chouinard with unidentified female singer, both in costume, possibly as characters in The Mikado, 1959 September, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Binghamton (N.Y.) On verso: Opera Guild party, Binghamton, N.Y. during Butterfly run, Sept. 59. (Box 1, Image 015)
  - Joseph Chouinard (center) in costume in the role of Bonze in Puccini's Madame Butterfly, presented by the Tri-Cities Opera Company, 1959 October, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Binghamton (N.Y.) Venue: Masonic Temple (Binghamton, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 016)
  - Joseph Chouinard (left), Gene Talley-Schmidt (3rd from left) and two unidentified males in costume in a production of Romberg's The student prince at Chastain Park, Atlanta, 1961, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Miller, Marc Location: Atlanta (Ga.) Venue: Chastain Memorial Park (Atlanta, Ga.) (Box 1, Image 017)
  - Prompter of the Tri-Cities Opera Company (probably John Sportelli), undated, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Binghamton (N.Y.) Venue: Masonic Temple (Binghamton, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 018)
  - Joseph Chouinard (3rd from left) in costume as the character Talpa in Tri-Cities Opera production of Puccini's Il Tabarro, 1961 March, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Binghamton (N.Y.) Venue: Masonic Temple (Binghamton, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 019)
  - The character Violetta Valery (either Rosalie DeFelice or Lois Crane) in a Tri-Cities Opera production Puccini's La Traviata, 1961 October, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Binghamton (N.Y.) Venue: Masonic Temple (Binghamton, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 020)
  - Joseph Chouinard (2nd from left) as Dr. Grenvil in the Tri-Cities Opera production of Verdi's La Traviata, 1961 October, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Binghamton (N.Y.) Venue: Masonic Temple (Binghamton, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 021)
  - Portrait of Joseph Chouinard, 1964 December, 1 Portrait photographs; Photographer: Delmar Studio (Binghamton, N.Y.) Location: Binghamton (N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 022)
  - Joseph Chouinard (left) as the character Polyphemus and Lawrence Bennett as Acis in a production of Handel's Acis and Galatea, 1967 January, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Sladin, V. Location: New York (N.Y.) Venue: Minor Latham Playhouse (Box 1, Image 023)
  - Joseph Chouinard (left) as the character Polyphemus and Lawrence Bennett as Acis in a production of Handel's Acis and Galatea, 1967 January, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Sladin, V. Location: New York (N.Y.) Venue: Minor Latham Playhouse (Box 1, Image 024)
  - Lawrence Bennett as the character Acis in a production of Handel's Acis and Galatea, 1967 January, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Sladin, V. Location: New York (N.Y.) Venue: Minor Latham Playhouse (Box 1, Image 025)
  - Lawrence Bennett as the character Acis in a production of Handel's Acis and Galatea, 1967 January, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Sladin, V. Location: New York (N.Y.) Venue: Minor Latham Playhouse (Box 1, Image 026)
  - Lawrence Bennett as the character Acis in a production of Handel's Acis and Galatea, 1967 January, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Sladin, V. Location: New York (N.Y.) Venue: Minor Latham Playhouse (Box 1, Image 027)
  - Lawrence Bennett as the character Acis in a production of Handel's Acis and Galatea, 1967 January, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Sladin, V. Location: New York (N.Y.) Venue: Minor Latham Playhouse (Box 1, Image 028)
  - Portrait of Joseph Chouinard, 1974 October, 1 Portrait photographs; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Buffalo (N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 029)
  - In Soo Park as the character Rodolfo and Rachel Lewis as Mimi in Act 1 of a University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 030)
  - In Soo Park as the character Rodolfo and Rachel Lewis as Mimi in Act 1 of a University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 031)
  - Opening of Act 2 of University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 032)
  - Scene from Act 2 of University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 033)
  - Joseph Chouinard (far right) as the character Colline in Act 2 of University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 034)
  - Jane Bane (center) as the character Musetta and Joseph Chouinard (far right) as Colline in Act 2 of University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 035)
  - Jane Bane (center) as the character Musetta, with In Soo Park as Rodolfo and Rachel Lewis as Mimi (seated at table), and Joseph Chouinard (far right) as Colline in Act 2 of University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 036)
  - In Soo Park (left) as the character Rodolfo and George Wands in Act 3 of University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 037)
  - In Soo Park as the character Rodolfo and Rachel Lewis as Mimi in Act 3 of a University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 038)
  - In Soo Park (right) as the character Rodolfo and George Wands in Act 3 of University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 039)
  - Kenneth Friesema as Schaunard, Joseph Chouinard as Colline, In Soo Park as Rodolfo, and George Wands as Marcello in Act 4 of University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 040)
  - Kenneth Friesema as Schaunard, George Wands as Marcello, In Soo Park as Rodolfo, Rachel Lewis as Mimi, and Joseph Chouinard as Colline in Act 4 of University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 041)
  - Rachel Lewis as Mimi, Joseph Chouinard as Colline, and Kenneth Friesema as Schaunard in Act 4 of University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 042)
  - In Soo Park as Rodolfo and Rachel Lewis as Mimi in Act 4 of University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 043)
  - In Soo Park as Rodolfo and Rachel Lewis as Mimi in Act 4 of University at Buffalo production of Puccini's La Boheme, 1974 November, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Willoughby, Robert Location: Williamsville (N.Y.) Venue: Williamsville North High School (Williamsville, N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 044)
  - Joseph Chouinard and Ethelmae Mason on steps of a church, 2006 May, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: New York (N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 045)
  - Joseph Chouinard sitting at a table in Ethelmae Mason's home, 2006 May, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: New York (N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 046)
  - Joseph Chouinard shaking hands with the operator of a pedi-cab in New York City, 2006 May, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: New York (N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 047)
- Medium format photographs, circa 1944-1996, II.; Item 048-069
  - Portrait of Thomas J. Chouinard in United States Marine uniform, circa 1944, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Unknown location (Box 1, Image 048)
  - Joseph Chouinard holding a viola, 1954, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Unknown location (Box 1, Image 049)
  - Aspen Music School Opera workshop production of Bizet's The Pearl fishers, 1962 August, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Aspen (Colo.) Venue: Wheeler Opera House (Aspen, Colo.) (Box 1, Image 050)
  - Joseph Chouinard as the character of the General in the Aspen Music School Opera Workshop's production of Henri Sauguet's La Contrebasse, 1962 July, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Aspen (Colo.) Venue: Wheeler Opera House (Aspen, Colo.) (Box 1, Image 051)
  - Joseph Chouinard as the character of the General in the Aspen Music School Opera Workshop's production of Henri Sauguet's La Contrebasse, 1962 July, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Aspen (Colo.) Venue: Wheeler Opera House (Aspen, Colo.) (Box 1, Image 052)
  - Joseph Chouinard as the character of the General in the Aspen Music School Opera Workshop's production of Henri Sauguet's La Contrebasse, 1962 July, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Aspen (Colo.) Venue: Wheeler Opera House (Aspen, Colo.) (Box 1, Image 053)
  - Composer Ross Lee Finney (left) and vocalist Joseph Chouinard at a rehearsal for the premiere performance of Finney's The nun's priest tale at Dartmouth's Congregation of the Arts, 1965 August, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Image 054)
  - Composer Ross Lee Finney (left) and vocalist Joseph Chouinard at a rehearsal for the premiere performance of Finney's The nun's priest's tale at Dartmouth's Congregation of the Arts, 1965 August, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Hanover (N.H.) Venue: Hopkins Center (Box 1, Image 055)
  - Composer Ross Lee Finney (left) and vocalist Joseph Chouinard at a rehearsal for the premiere performance of Finney's The nun's priest's tale at Dartmouth's Congregation of the Arts, 1965 August, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Hanover (N.H.) Venue: Hopkins Center (Box 1, Image 056)
  - Allan Evans (left) and Joseph Chouinard in the world premiere performance of Ross Lee Finney's The nun's priest's tale at Dartmouth's Congregation of the Arts, 1965 August 21, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Hanover (N.H.) Venue: Hopkins Center (Box 1, Image 057)
  - Allan Evans (left) and Joseph Chouinard, with narrator Michael Best in the background in the world premiere performance of Ross Lee Finney's The nun's priest's tale at Dartmouth's Congregation of the Arts, 1965 August 21, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Hanover (N.H.) Venue: Hopkins Center (Box 1, Image 058)
  - Allan Evans, Joseph Chouinard, Michael Best, conductor Mario di Bonaventura, and the Dartmouth Symphony Orchestra in the world premiere performance of Ross Lee Finney's The nun's priest's tale at Dartmouth's Congregation of the Arts, 1965 August 21, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Hanover (N.H.) Venue: Hopkins Center (Box 1, Image 059)
  - Conductor Mario Di Bonaventura, composer Ross Lee Finney, baritone Allan Evans, bass Joseph Chouinard, and folksinger James W. Symington receiving applause after the world premiere performance of Finney's The nun's priest's tale at Dartmouth's Congregation of the Arts, 1965 August 21, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Hanover (N.H.) Venue: Hopkins Center (Box 1, Image 060)
  - Joseph Chouinard being served a dessert by an unidentified male, 1984, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Unknown location (Box 1, Image 061)
  - Joseph Chouinard and Ethelmae Mason seated outdoors, 1995 July, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Binghamton (N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 062)
  - View from apartment balcony of Manhattan Plaza and docks, circa 1995, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: New York (N.Y.) (Box 1, Image 063)
  - Joseph Chouinard speaking with tenor Robert White at a Bargemusic concert, 1996, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Brooklyn (N.Y.) Venue: Bargemusic (Box 1, Image 064)
  - View of the Brooklyn Bridge from Fulton Ferry, Brooklyn, 1996, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Brooklyn (N.Y.) Venue: Bargemusic (Box 1, Image 065)
  - Joseph Chouinard speaking with tenor Robert White at a Bargemusic concert, 1996, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Brooklyn (N.Y.) Venue: Bargemusic (Box 1, Image 066)
  - Violist Paul Neubauer in conversation with unidentified woman at a Bargemusic concert, 1996, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Brooklyn (N.Y.) Venue: Bargemusic (Box 1, Image 067)
  - Violinist Mark Peskanov at a Bargemusic concert, 1996, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Brooklyn (N.Y.) Venue: Bargemusic (Box 1, Image 068)
  - Tenor Robert White in conversation at a Bargemusic concert, 1996, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Brooklyn (N.Y.) Venue: Bargemusic (Box 1, Image 069)
- Smaller format photographs, circa 1928-circa 1981, III.; Item 070-200
  - Joseph Chouinard (right) and his brother Thomas, circa 1928, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Middletown (Conn.) (Box 1, Image 070)
  - Joseph Chouinard (left) and his brother Thomas, circa 1928, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Middletown (Conn.) (Box 1, Image 071)
  - Joseph Chouinard (right) and his brother Thomas, with an unidentified woman, probably Elizabeth Bradley, their adoptive mother, circa 1928, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Middletown (Conn.) (Box 1, Image 072)
  - Joseph Chouinard (right) and his brother Thomas on the steps of a house, circa 1928, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Middletown (Conn.) (Box 1, Image 073)
  - Joseph Chouinard (left) and his brother Thomas, circa 1928, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Middletown (Conn.) (Box 1, Image 074)
  - Thomas and Joseph Chouinard playing with a cat, circa 1929, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Middletown (Conn.) On verso: Shirley Gustafson (Box 1, Image 075)
  - Joseph Chouinard (left) and his brother Thomas, 1931, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Middletown (Conn.) On verso: Middletown, Ct. 215 Prospect St. (Box 1, Image 076)
  - Joseph Chouinard standing next to a house, 1931 February, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Location: Middletown (Conn.) (Box 1, Image 077)